Chapter 6, the L. The tongue tip touches the ridge, even at the end of a word. This
chapter discusses the sound of L, not to be confused with that of the American R,
which was covered in the last chapter. We'll approach this sound first by
touching on the difficulties it presents to foreign speakers of English, and next
by comparing L to the related sounds of T, D, and N. L and foreign speakers of
English. The English L is usually no problem at the beginning or in the middle
of a word. The native language of some people, however, causes them to make their
English L much too short. At the end of a word, the L is especially noticeable if it
is either missing, Chinese, or too short, Spanish. In addition, most people consider
the L as a simple consonant. This can also cause a lot of trouble. Thus, two things
are at work here. Location of language sounds in the mouth, and the complexity of
the L sound. Location of language in the mouth. The sounds of many Romance
languages are generally located far forward in the mouth. My French teacher
told me that if I couldn't see my lips when I spoke French, it wasn't French.
Spanish is sometimes even called the smiling language. Chinese, on the other
hand, is similar to American English in that it's mostly produced far back in the
mouth. The principal difference is that English It also requires clear use of the
tongue's tip, a large component of the sound of L. The compound sound of L. The L
is not a simple consonant. It's a compound made up of a vowel and a consonant. Like
the a sound, the sound of L is a combination of uh and ul. The uh, being a
reduced vowel sound, is created in the throat, but the ul part requires a clear
movement of the tongue. First, the tip must touch behind the teeth. This part is
simple enough. The back of the tongue must drop down and back for the continuing
schwa sound. Especially at the end of a word, Spanish-speaking people tend to
leave out the schwa and shorten the L, and Chinese speakers usually leave it off
entirely. One way to avoid the pronunciation difficulty of a final L, as
in call, is to make a liaison when the next word begins with a vowel. For
example, if you want to say, I have to call on my friend, let the liaison do your
work for you. Say, I have to call on my friend.